<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nationalism on Ticki&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>http://ticki.github.io/tags/nationalism/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nationalism on Ticki&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://ticki.github.io/tags/nationalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Veterans are not blameless</title>
      <link>http://ticki.github.io/blog/veterans-are-not-blameless/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ticki.github.io/blog/veterans-are-not-blameless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In USA, no matter where you go, you will find people praising veterans, the millitary, and war in general to an almost masturbatory extent. This mentality is now spreading to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do I find it tiring, I find it disgusting. I have to admit it: I feel little sympathy with the veterans of fighting imperialist powers. They don&#39;t serve their nation; they serve their elites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply cannot put myself into the hivemind of imperialism disguised as patriotism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some opinions you simply cannot express in the west — and this is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cruelty-of-war&#34;&gt;Cruelty of war&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you list the wars in the last 50 years of the world powers, you will find none which is not motivated by money, power, or natural resources. None of the recent wars have been acts of humanitarianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the popular believe, wars are not an act between soldiers. Civilians die en masse as well. It is simply impossible to avoid this. You cannot go to war with another state without going to war with its people as well, which is exactly &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; war is inheritly cruel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;patriotism&#34;&gt;Patriotism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriotism is a tool of the elites. It is manipulated and constructed as such. It is the very epitome of hivemind. It is used to condemn resistance, support war, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Support the troops&amp;quot; is more-or-less equivalent to &amp;quot;support the imperialist wars pushed by the elites&amp;quot;, because without such wars, there would be no need for the troops you&#39;re supposed to support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blame-the-game-not-the-player&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Blame the game not the player&amp;quot;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, this is a good argument for supporting veterans, however I don&#39;t think you can plead ignorance in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is simply too information available on the subject, and you cannot strip responsibility from an adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldiers are puppets of the elites for the elites. They don&#39;t plan the war nor push the imperailist ideas, but they do all the dirty work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end of the day, they are murderers. A murderer truely believing, he is doing good, is still a murderer; evil is not justified by belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;duty-to-resist&#34;&gt;Duty to resist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even under conscription, you can still resist. This is true in every western country. The president of USA will certainly know this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can even resist without punishment. It is safe to say, that it is easy and cheap to avoid conscription. It requires little effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the USA, there isn&#39;t even a conscription currently. It is thus totally voluntary. You have to actively choose to go to war (rather than passively not dodging the draft).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;forgiveness&#34;&gt;Forgiveness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But make no mistake, even if the individual is well aware of the horrors, they can still be manipulated into evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism, nationalism, racism, and mindless patriotism are all ideologies and ideas which can be imposed on people to justify their action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Noam Chomsky wrote a whole book on this, &amp;quot;Manufactoring Consent&amp;quot;. He argues that education, media, etc. are all tools to impose these ideas on us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the soldier might not have acted in bad faith. And if that matters (which I personally think it does to some extent), they deserve to be forgived. But to be forgived, you must admit to your mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many veterans won&#39;t do so, most still support the causes of the war, they served in, and thus approve of the imperialist force, they helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-words&#34;&gt;Final words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make it clear, that I&#39;m not saying that the countless lives of soldiers lost in war is good in any way. I don&#39;t believe in death penality, so I naturally don&#39;t hope nor cheer for their death, which is disrespectful to their family and loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you lost someone to war, you have my condolences. However, I won&#39;t support the veterans nor the troops or any of the work they did. They were paid and knew what they did.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>