<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Concurrency on Ticki&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>http://ticki.github.io/tags/concurrency/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Concurrency on Ticki&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ticki.github.io/tags/concurrency/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fearless concurrency with hazard pointers</title>
      <link>http://ticki.github.io/blog/an-efficient-hazard-based-concurrent-memory-reclamation-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ticki.github.io/blog/an-efficient-hazard-based-concurrent-memory-reclamation-system/</guid>
      <description>For those who don&#39;t know, I am working on a file system, TFS, which employs various concurrent structures to improve performance. Whenever you do this kind of advanced concurrency, you will meet the ABA problem, roughly describable as &amp;quot;what if another thread runs the destructor on a value you are reading?&amp;quot;
What this problem is, and how can it be solved, is what this blog post will investigate. It presents a form of an optimized form of hazard-pointers as well as an implementation thereof.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Atomic Hash Table</title>
      <link>http://ticki.github.io/blog/an-atomic-hash-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ticki.github.io/blog/an-atomic-hash-table/</guid>
      <description>In programs where there is some kind of global state, you will often find the need for having a key-value map; you could for example imagine keeping some kind of cache of a bunch of entries from database table. Obviously, you&#39;d just use a hash table, easy right?
Not really. Imagine that there is multiple threads. One approach is to wrap it in a mutex to ensure thread safety, but that would kind of miss the point of concurrency: It wouldn&#39;t be concurrent, it would just be blocking.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>